<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NLP on SeHe&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/nlp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NLP on SeHe&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LDA and WordCloud on Mastodon Posts for the Bavarian State Election!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mastodonbavarian_election_lda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mastodonbavarian_election_lda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We selected a party as the dominant party, when this party or its&#xA;candidate was mentioned 50 % or more compared to other parties. But this&#xA;results in many posts that mention the candidates Söder, Aiwanger,&#xA;although the post is attribute to different parties. This mixed&#xA;attribution, which allows to mention different parties as long as there&#xA;is a clear dominant party, makes attribution hard, but was used to keep&#xA;as many posts as possible. Even though in some weeks we did not record&#xA;post for some smaller &amp;quot;dominant&amp;quot; parties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mastodon - Election Predictions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mastodon_on_bavarian_elecvtion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mastodon_on_bavarian_elecvtion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I held a presentation on this project on Elixir MeetUp Berlin on Feb 8th, 2024. The slides can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sehHeiden/MeetUpElixir/blob/main/presentation_MastodonElection.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Livebook code can be found &lt;a href=&#34;election_bavaria.livemd&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;The code for data collection can be found &lt;a href=&#34;./mastodon&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We try to predict voting result in the 2023 Bavarian state election in Germany by Mastodon posts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last polls before the election show an average error of about 0.7 to 0.9 percent per major party. A time weighted average of the polls of the last six weeks before the election reduced the error to 0.39 percentage points per party.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
