<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GIS on SeHe&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/gis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in GIS on SeHe&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/gis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Speed Comparision on some Modern GIS tools</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/speed_comparision_gis_intersection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/speed_comparision_gis_intersection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;GIS can change with current technology as Apache Arrow, and perhaps also Apache Spark und Apache Sedona.&#xA;Also in Pythonland Geopandas enhanced performance over time. In addition, I also wanted to try Dask und DuckDB.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please contact me, when you read this and think I could have increased the code quality and speed.&#xA;I use some public data, which still widely use shape files in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-data&#34;&gt;The Data&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First I load fhe ALKIS (register) building data for all counties in the state of Brandenburg.&#xA;All vector files are open data. The victor files are still offered as Shapefiles.&#xA;From the ALKIS Dataset of Brandenburg I used the buildings and the parcels (with land usage).&#xA;The files are stored per county!&#xA;The geometries have some errors which Geopandas auto-detects and fixes.&#xA;In addition, some file can not be opened with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fiona.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html&#34;&gt;fiona&lt;/a&gt; library from Geopandas, with the error message&#xA;of multiple  geometry columns. Hence, we always use de new default: pyogrio.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Least Cost Path for Optimisation on Paths for Power Cables in North Germany</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cableroute/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cableroute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;sec:introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction and Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The German power system is adding renewable energy sources in the north,&#xA;where wind energy plants reach their highest efficiency, due to higher&#xA;wind speeds. At the same time old power plants e.g. nuclear, hard coal&#xA;and lignite are being phased out [^eser-frey_analyzing_2012]. These&#xA;older power plants were mainly located in southern and central Germany.&#xA;The energy sink, industrial and private demand, is not shifting north.&#xA;Therefore, the renewable energy has to be transported from north to&#xA;south which increases the congestion in the power grid. The amount of&#xA;offshore wind power, that the German energy system can use, can be&#xA;greatly increased by adding new power lines &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
