<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on SeHe's Blog</title><link>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on SeHe's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Speed Comparison on some Modern GIS tools</title><link>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/speed_comparision_gis_intersection/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/speed_comparision_gis_intersection/</guid><description>&lt;p>GIS can change with current technology such as Apache Arrow, and perhaps also with some other techniques.
In Pythonland, Geopandas has improved performance over time. I also wanted to try Dask, DuckDB and Apache Sedona.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Please contact me if you read this and think I could have improved the code quality and speed.
I use some public data, which is still widely used in Germany as shape files.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update&lt;/strong>: In the previous version I was not able to save to geoparquet with DuckDB. It works, it can be openmed inm QGIS, not so far no CRS.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>LDA and WordCloud on Mastodon Posts for the Bavarian State Election!</title><link>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/mastodonbavarian_election_lda/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/mastodonbavarian_election_lda/</guid><description>&lt;p>We selected a party as the dominant party, when this party or its
candidate was mentioned 50 % or more compared to other parties. But this
results in many posts that mention the candidates Söder, Aiwanger,
although the post is attribute to different parties. This mixed
attribution, which allows to mention different parties as long as there
is a clear dominant party, makes attribution hard, but was used to keep
as many posts as possible. Even though in some weeks we did not record
post for some smaller &amp;quot;dominant&amp;quot; parties.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mastodon - Election Predictions</title><link>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/mastodon_on_bavarian_elecvtion/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/mastodon_on_bavarian_elecvtion/</guid><description>&lt;p>I held a presentation on this project on Elixir MeetUp Berlin on Feb 8th, 2024. The slides can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/sehHeiden/MeetUpElixir/blob/main/presentation_MastodonElection.pdf">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Livebook code can be found &lt;a href="election_bavaria.livemd">here&lt;/a>.
The code for data collection can be found &lt;a href="./mastodon">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>We try to predict voting result in the 2023 Bavarian state election in Germany by Mastodon posts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The last polls before the election show an average error of about 0.7 to 0.9 percent per major party. A time weighted average of the polls of the last six weeks before the election reduced the error to 0.39 percentage points per party.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Least Cost Path for Optimisation on Paths for Power Cables in North Germany</title><link>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/cableroute/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sehheiden.github.io/posts/cableroute/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="sec:introduction">Introduction and Objectives&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The German power system is adding renewable energy sources in the north,
where wind energy plants reach their highest efficiency, due to higher
wind speeds. At the same time old power plants e.g. nuclear, hard coal
and lignite are being phased out &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. These
older power plants were mainly located in southern and central Germany.
The energy sink, industrial and private demand, is not shifting north.
Therefore, the renewable energy has to be transported from north to
south which increases the congestion in the power grid. The amount of
offshore wind power, that the German energy system can use, can be
greatly increased by adding new power lines &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>